# AGUSTIN GUERRA

304-871-1833 | agustinguerra@ufl.edu | LinkedIn | Website

#### PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Highly motivated engineering professional with 5+ years of experience in the transportation industry and +4 years of research experience in traffic engineering. Committed to providing high-quality service focusing on innovation, safety, sustainability, operational performance, diversity, equity, and inclusion. Currently conducting research about optimization of traffic operations considering connected and automated vehicles (CAVs).

#### EDUCATION

PhD in Civil Engineering University of Florida **MS in Civil Engineering** University of Kansas **BS in Civil Engineering** 

Universidad Tecnologica de Panama

Aug. 2019 – Expected May 2023 Gainesville, FL Aug. 2017 - May 2019 Lawrence, KS Mar. 2008 - May 2013 Panama, PA

### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

Expertise: Transportation Engineering, Statistical Analysis, Operation Research, Machine Learning

**Programming and Statistical Languages**: Python (+3 years), R (1 year)

**Software**: MS Office, SPSS

**Developer Tools**: Github, Visual Studio Code

Scientific Python Libraries: Pandas, NumPy, Matplotlib, CPLEX, sci-kit learn, TensorFlow, Selenium, webdrivermanager, xml

#### EXPERIENCE

#### **Graduate Research Assistant**

Aug. 2019 - Present Gainesville, FL

University of Florida

- Performed all phases of the research process, including problem definition, literature review, research design, data collection, analysis of results, and preparation of reports
- Developed optimization algorithms in Python for arterials considering CAVs capabilities
- · Developed, maintained, updated, and documented the development of simulation algorithms in Python for the evaluation of CAVs control strategies
- · Performed unit, integration, story, and acceptance tests of numerical simulations for CAVs
- Assisted in the implementation of optimization algorithm for isolated intersections in a microsimulation software
- Formulated different optimization models to reduce intersection delays, including LP, IP, and MILP models
- Developed heuristic methods using search-based algorithms to reduce delays in arterials
- Developed a Python-based data pipeline to extract CAVs trajectories from connected vehicles
- Implemented various techniques for data preprocessing, including data normalization, outlier detection and removal, and feature selection, to ensure the quality and integrity of the data prior to analysis
- Evaluated machine learning algorithms to estimate the occurrence of future crashes
- Facilitated the coordination of projects' activities to meet deadlines

# **Highway & Traffic Consultant**

May 2019 - Aug. 2019

Panama

• Provided safety assessment for roadways, interchanges, and intersections

· Developed geometric design proposals

# **Highway Engineer**

**WSP** 

Nov. 2012 - Aug. 2017

- Louis Berger Panama • Led the development of highway design projects. Project portfolio comprises several projects in
  - the Latin American region (Panama, Colombia, Honduras, and Peru) adding up to \$3 billion in construction amount Coordinated with different departments (geotechnical, hydraulic, and pavement) to meet deadlines
  - Facilitated the establishment of a new business unit in Bogota, Colombia
  - Supervised and provided mentorship to a team of four drafters, contributing to their professional development, and ensuring project deliverables met quality standards

# LEADERSHIP/INVOLVEMENT

<b>Founding Member and Chair of the IEEE-ITSS Student Chapter</b> : Led the efforts to establish an IEEE Student Chapter branch of the Intelligent Transportation Systems Society ( <u>ITSS</u> ) at the University of Florida	2021 – 2022
ITE University Chapter Vice President: Coordinated student seminars and ITE activities	2021 – 2022
<b>Student Representative at the UFTI Internal Steering <u>Committee</u></b> : Promoted engagement activities between industry professionals and students	2020 – 2022
<b>Media Manager at KU Fulbright Student <u>Association</u></b> : Led dissemination of activities promoted by the Fulbright Student Board, 2018	2018 – 2019
FELLOWSHIPS & AWARDS	
ITS Florida Anne Brewer Academic Scholarships: Awarded by the ITS Florida Chapter	2022
<b>Second Place, IEEE-ITSS Logo Design Competition</b> : Awarded by the IEEE Intelligent Transportation Systems Society ( <u>ITSS</u> )	2022
Fulbright Fellowship: Awarded by the U.S Bureau of Educational and Cultural Affairs	2017
<b>Global Best Project</b> : Awarded by the <u>ENR</u> for the Coastal Beltway project in Panama	2015
<b>Petroterminal of Panama Scholarship</b> : Awarded by the Petroterminal of Panama ( <u>PTP</u> ) to complete a Bachelors's Degree at the Universidad Tecnologica de Panama	2009
Purications	

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

#### **Peer-Reviewed Journals**

- [1] **Guerra, A.**, L. Elefeteriadou. Platooning Trajectory Optimization for Connected Automated Vehicles in Coordinated-Arterials. *Transportation Research Record*, 2022
- [2] **Guerra, A.**, V. Gadhiya, P. Srisurin. Crash Prediction on Road Segments Using Machine Learning Methods. *ASEAN Engineering Journal*, 2022.

# **Conference Proceedings**

[1] L. Carvalho, **Guerra, A.**, X. Wang, P. Manjunatha, L. Elefteriadou. Simulation Platform for Testing and Evaluation of CAV Trajectory Optimization and Signal Control Algorithm Integrated with Commercial Traffic Simulator. *Proceedings of the 2022 Winter Simulation Conference* 

### PROFESSIONAL SOCIETIES

IEEE: Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers	2022 – Present
IEEE-ITSS: IEEE Intelligent Transportation Systems Society	2022 – Present
ASCE: American Society of Civil Engineers	2022 – 2023
ITE: Institute of Transportation Engineers	2019 – Present

## **REFERENCES**

**Lily Elefteriadou, PhD**: Barbara Goldsby Professor, University of Florida **Juliana Canas**: Senior Advisor, First Climate

Julio Aysa: Env./Social and Governance Lead Officer, IDB

elefter@ce.ufl.edu juliana.canas-vanegas@firstclimate.com jaysa71@yahoo.com.mx